A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Kilolo Kijakazi FA1848
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Kilolo Kijakazi
1987-2014
Rockefeller Archive Center
Kijakazi, Kilolo
Ford Foundation
FA1848
36.5 Cubic Feet 93 boxes (81 letter document boxes, 11 legal document boxes, 1 oversize document box)
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the subject files of Kilolo Kijakazi who served as a program officer within the Asset Building and Community Development division in the Economic Development department at the Ford Foundation. Kijakazi was key in determining the future of grantmaking in the Financial Assets unit starting in 2003. The collection spans from 1987-2014.
The collection includes grant working files, proposals, reports, conference materials, and correspondence.
The focus of Kijakazi's work was funding programs that provided pathways for low- and moderate-income families to build wealth. The Ford Foundation-funded initiatives that provided backing for this work included Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship and Downpayment (SEED), Building Economic Security Over a Lifetime (BESOL), and the American Dream Demonstration (ADD). These programs supported research and demonstrations of Child Development Accounts (CDAs), Child Savings Accounts (CSA), and Individual Development Accounts (IDA), efforts to preserve and improve Social Security benefits, educating policymakers in economic security issues at the state and federal level, provided grants to organizations involved in researching efforts to improve economic security, and supported grassroots efforts to improve asset building at the local and state level.
The collection also highlights Kijakazi's and the Ford Foundation's efforts to fund programs to close the racial wealth gap and utilize the expertise of, and build opportunities for, people of color in the research, policy, and practice of asset building work. The programs aimed to create universal, inclusive, and progressive saving and asset building policy in the U.S.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Rockefeller Archive Center received five accessions containing Kilolo Kijakazi's files from the Ford Foundation between 2020 and 2022: Accessions 2020:006, 2020:024, 2021:080, 2021:104, and 2022:029.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in one series with subseries organized by grantee, Ford-funded initiatives, and supporting documents.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation's Asset Building and Community Development division in the Economic Development department supported several large-scale initiatives involving grants to multiple grantees in the 2000s through the 2010s.
In 2002, the Ford Foundation provided $6.1 million to the American Dream Demonstration (ADD) project that tested the potential impact of individual development accounts (IDAs) on individual savings behaviors in 14 programs across the United States.
Beginning in 2003, the Foundation supported the Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship, and Downpayment Initiative (SEED). SEED was a 10-year national policy, practice, and research program to develop, test and promote matched savings accounts and financial education for children. One of the first goals of the program was to build the capacity of the Corporation for Economic Development (CFED) (renamed Prosperity Now in 2017) and the Center for Social Development (CSD) at Washington University in St. Louis. Other areas of SEED investment included 10 small-scale pilot projects administered by local foundations, a project focused on Head Start Centers in Michigan, a project that partnered with the State of Oklahoma (SEED for Oklahoma Kids) to provide savings accounts to children at birth, work by the New America Foundation to advocate for legislation, and funding for the Initiative on Financial Security (IFS) at the Aspen Institute. Ultimately, the Ford Foundation provided more than $30 million in support of the program.
In 2004, Ford funded a series of focus groups with different communities of color to determine the future directions of Financial Assets programming. Ford also supported annual convenings of experts of color in the field of asset building starting in 2004.
In 2009, Ford launched the Building Economic Security Over a Lifetime (BESOL) initiative to support research on saving and asset policy as well as local grassroots efforts, develop widespread support for state policy to create life cycle savings accounts, develop communications infrastructure linking national and state policy organizations, and fund research and advocacy to protect and improve Social Security. A focus of the program was to create a pipeline of scholars in the field of asset building from diverse backgrounds. The experts represented Black, Latin American, Native American, Native Hawaiian, Asian American, and Pacific Islander communities.
The Ford Foundation also provided grants to many other organizations involved in asset building work, including the following:
The Urban Institute's Academy for Public Policy Analysis and Research
National Academy of Social Insurance (NASI) for educating policymakers on the importance of Social Security to low-income families
Howard University's Center on Race and Wealth
Tuskegee University for recovery efforts following Hurricanes Katrina and Rita
Center for Social Development at Washington University
University of Michigan's Research and Training Program on Poverty and Public Policy
Earned Assets Resources Network (EARN)
Illinois Asset Building Group (IABG)
First Nations Development Institute
Center for Public Policy Priorities
Southern Regional Asset Building Coalition (SRABC)
Center for Community Change (CCC)
PolicyLink to build a communications system that would create an accountable public policy process
Duke University Research Network on Racial and Ethnic Inequality to measure the wealth gap by race, ethnicity, country of origin, and Native American tribal affiliation
Opportunity Agenda to develop a communications strategy and set of messages on the racial wealth gap.
Diversity (Grantmaking); Economic development; Economic policy -- Research; Financial policy; Individual development accounts; Pensions; Saving and investment; Savings accounts -- Children -- United States; Social security; Wealth--Research--United States
- Grant Working Files and Ford Foundation Initiatives, 1987-2014; 1; 37.3 Cubic Feet
  - Abt Associates, Inc., 1998-2005; 1
    Scope and Contents
    ABT Associates, Inc. (09801647), 1998 July 01-2003 December 31
    Partial support for an evaluation of individual development accounts
    - Evaluation of the American Dream Demonstration, Financial and Narrative Reports, Ford Foundation Grant Number 0980-1647-2, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Draft Final American Dream Demonstration Report and Data Quality Issues, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Interim American Dream Demonstration Report and Data Quality Issues, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Frank's (Frank DeGiovanni) File on Data Quality for American Dream Demonstration Study, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - American Dream Demonstration Ford Foundation Grant 0980-1647, 1998-2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Center on Budget and Policy Priorities, 1997-2005; 2
    Center on Budget and Policy Priorities (09701367), 1997 June 01-2005 May 31
    Support for a research project on American social welfare policy
    - 2004 Annual Report (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Working File, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Supplement 3 to Grant Number 0970-1367, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Grant Notification Letters, 1997-2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Grant Status Report, 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Consumer Federation of America, 1999-2007; 3
    Grant Number 09901112, 1999 June 01-2003 November 30
    Support to plan a national marketing effort to promote savings among the least affluent and conduct a pilot program in Cleveland
    Grant Number 10400329, 2004 January 01-2006 December 31
    For a demonstration campaign in Cleveland to promote savings among the least affluent and to evaluate the effectiveness of this strategy for building assets
    - Working File 0990-1112-2, 2003-2007 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Working File 1040-0329-0, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Consumer Federation of America (10400329), 2004 January 01-2006 December 31
    - Reports and Notes, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - 400,000 America Saves Phase III, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - History, 1999-2002 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Grant Number 0990-1112 - Grant Status Reports, Articles, Memos, and Grant Approval Documents, 2001-2003 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Corporation for Enterprise Development, 2001-2005; 4
    In 2017, the organization CFED (Corporation for Enterprise Development) rebranded to Prosperity Now.
    Grant 09901175, 1999 July 01-2010 November 30
    Support for CFED's initiative to promote savings and asset-building programs for low-income populations to policy makers and other audiences nationwide
    Grant 09701062, 1997 May 01-2002 June 30
    Partial support for a national demonstration and evaluation of individual development accounts (9601353)
    Grant 10200714, 2002 April 01-2010 August 31
    Core support for a national "SEED" demonstration (Savings for Education, Entrepreneurship and Downpayment) to explore the potential of Children's Savings Accounts
    - Growing Wealth Working Group, 2002-2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Staffing and Finance Issues, 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Policy Grant Supplement, 2001-2003 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Progress Reports Grant 970-1062-2, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Request for Core Support and Policy Work - Grant 0990-1175, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      Corporation for Enterprise Development (09901175), 1999 July 01-2010 November 30
    - Grant for Work with Financial Institutions, Financial Institutions Working Group (FIWG), 2001-2003 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - State Report Card Presentation, 2005 February 14 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Individual Development Account (IDA) Interest Group Forum, 2003 September 15 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Emails and Notes, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Assets for Independence Act (AFIA), undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Individual Development Account (IDA) Certification Standards, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Publications, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Grant Number 0990-1175 - RGAs and Memos, Program Action Sheets, and Grant Status Report, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship and Downpayment (SEED) Policy Demonstration Finalists, 2003 (Box 72, Folder 641)
    - Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship, and Downpayment (SEED) Request for Proposals (RFP) Invitation List and Analysis, 2002 July (Box 72, Folder 642)
    - Working Papers for the Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship, and Downpayment (SEED) Policy Demonstration, 2001 November (Box 72, Folder 643-644)
    - Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship and Downpayment (SEED) Advisory Committee - Grant Information for Downpayments on an American Dream Policy Demonstration (ADD), 2003 (Box 72, Folder 645)
    - Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship, and Downpayment (SEED) - Proposals and Progress Report, 2001-2003 (Box 72, Folder 646)
      Corporation for Enterprise Development (09701062), 1997 May 01-2002 June 30
      Partial support for a national demonstration and evaluation of individual development accounts (960-1353)
      Corporation for Enterprise Development (10200714), 2002 April 01-2010 August 31
    - Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship, and Downpayment (SEED) - Children's Savings Account Research (Domestic), 1998-2001 (Box 72, Folder 647)
    - Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship, and Downpayment (SEED) - England's Children's Savings Accounts Research, 2000-2004 (Box 73, Folder 648)
    - Center for Social Development on Children's Savings Accounts and 529 Plans, 2003-2004 (Box 73, Folder 649)
    - Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship and Downpayment (SEED) - Request for Proposals for Demonstration Sites, 2003 (Box 73, Folder 650)
    - Children's Savings Accounts (CSA) - Rationale for Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship and Downpayment (SEED) Demonstration, 2000-2002 (Box 73, Folder 651)
    - Children's Savings Accounts (CSA) - Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship and Downpayment (SEED) Demonstration, 2000-2002 (Box 73, Folder 652)
    - Children's Savings Accounts (CSA) - Field Scan Consultancy, 2001 (Box 73, Folder 653)
    - Children's Savings Accounts (CSA) - Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship and Downpayment (SEED) Advisory Board Memos, 2002-2003 (Box 73, Folder 654)
    - Children's Savings Accounts (CSA) - Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship and Downpayment (SEED) Site Selection, 2003 (Box 73, Folder 655)
    - Children's Savings Accounts (CSA) - Planning, 2001 (Box 73, Folder 656)
    - Children's Savings Accounts (CSA) - Meeting Notes, 2000-2002 (Box 74, Folder 657)
    - Grant to Center for Social Development (CSD) - Taking Children and Youth Asset Building to Scale: Inclusion in College Savings Plans, 2001-2003 (Box 74, Folder 658)
    - Individual Development Accounts (IDA) and Children's Savings Accounts (CSA) Reports and Working Papers, 2000-2005 (Box 74, Folder 659)
    - American Dream Demonstration (ADD) Wave 4 Proposal and Notes, 2006-2008 (Box 74, Folder 660)
    - Abt Associates and American Dream Demonstration (ADD) Evaluation Issues, 2004 (Box 74, Folder 661)
    - American Dream Demonstration (ADD) Research Papers by Center for Social Development (CSD), 2004 (Box 74, Folder 662)
    - American Dream Demonstration (ADD) Research Conference - Taking the Measure of the ADD: An Assessment of Knowledge Building and Impacts in Applied Social Research, 2005 April 20 (Box 74, Folder 663)
    - The Return of the Dream: An Analysis of the Probable Economic Return on a National Investment in Individual Development Accounts, 1995 May (Box 74, Folder 664)
    - Downpayments on the American Dream Demonstration (ADD) Policy Demonstration Request for Proposals and Summaries of American Dream Demonstration (ADD) Community Partners' Individual Development Accounts (IDA) Programs and Program Ideas, undated (Box 74, Folder 665)
    - Financial Innovations, 2001 (Box 74, Folder 666)
    - Recommendations for Grant Action, 1998-2002 (Box 74, Folder 667)
      Support for cfed's initiative to promote savings and asset-building programs for low-income populations to policy makers and other audiences nationwide
    - Individual Development Account (IDA) American Dream Demonstration (ADD) Proposal, 2001 (Box 75, Folder 668)
    - Directory of State Individual Development Account (IDA) Associations, 2001 November (Box 75, Folder 669)
  - Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (DAWN), 2000-2007; 5
    Grant 10450988, 2004 April 01-2005 March 31
    To mark DAWN's 20th anniversary with a program reflecting on new challenges for the international women's movement and engaging graduates of its first Training Institute in intergenerational dialogue
    Grant 10002028, 2000 October 01-2005 September 30
    Support for DAWN's research, training, and networking activities in developing countries worldwide
    - Next Steps, 2005-2007 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - 20th Anniversary, Cape Town, South Africa, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Proposal, Reports, and Newsletter, 2004-2006 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - 20th Anniversary, Grant Number 10450988, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Expenditure Responsibility Grantee, Grant Number 10002028, 2000-2005 (Box 5, Folder 34)
      Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (DAWN) (10002028), 2000 October 01-2005 September 30
  - Earned Assets Resources Network, 1999-2005; 6
    Grant to San Francisco Earned Asset Resource Network (10251708), 2003 January 15-2004 January 14
    To assess the feasibility of implementing individual development accounts and other asset building policies in California
    Grant 10400590, 2004 March 01-2010 September 30
    To implement a model strategy for achieving statewide saving and asset building policy in California
    - Working File (1040-0590-0), 2005 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - 2004 Supplement, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Grant Number 1025-1708, 1999-2002 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      San Francisco Earned Asset Resource Network (10251708), 2003 January 15-2004 January 14
    - San Francisco Asset Building Initiative, Ben Mangan, 2002 January (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - San Francisco Asset Building Initiative - Draft - Five Year Action Plan, 2001 January (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - First Nations Development Institute, 2000-2007; 7
    Grant 10350821, 2003 April 01-2005 March 31
    For activities to identify barriers to and opportunities for full access to state individual development account programs and funding mechanisms among Native American populations in Alaska and Oklahoma
    - Working File 1035-0821-1, 2005-2007 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      Grant 10350821, 2003 April 01-2005 March 31, For activities to identify barriers to and opportunities for full access to state individual development account programs and funding mechanisms among Native American populations in Alaska and Oklahoma
    - Owesta and Lakota, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Land Allotment and Title Issues, 2005 May 19 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Meeting with Sherry Salway Black, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Background on Organization, 2000-2004 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - First Nations Development Institute and The Ford Foundation, IDA Site Visit, Oklahoma, 2001 May 30-31 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Reports, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - D2D (Dare to Dream) Individual Development Accounts (IDA), Michele Kahane, Program Officer, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Earned Assets Resources Network (EARN) - Asset Policy Initiative of California (APIC) Task Force Meeting, 2003-2005 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Grant 1035-0821 - Grant Report and Program Action Sheets, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 49)
      First Nations Development Institute (10350821), 2003 April 01-2005 March 31
    - 2004 Grant Supplement, 2004-2005 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Pension Rights Center, 1994-2005; 8
    Grant 10001214, 2000 June 01-2007 June 30
    To convene a conference, a conversation on coverage, designed to begin the process of developing a consensus on proposals for increasing private pension coverage for low- and moderate-income workers
    - 2004 Supplement, 2004-2005 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Conversation on Coverage, 2003-2004 (Box 6, Folder 52-53)
    - October 23, 2003 Meeting, Proposal, and Miscellaneous Files Background Files (1000-1214), 2003-2004 (Box 6, Folder 54)
      Pension Rights Center (10001214), 2000 June 01-2007 June 30
    - Conversation on Coverage - Working Group Meeting Minutes, undated; CD (Box 6)
      Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
    - Grant Extension, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - 2002 Proposal, 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Conversation on Coverage, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Background, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Proposal, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Conversation on Coverage, 2000-2003 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - United Way of America, 1987-2006; 9
    Grant 10201378, 2002 July 01-2003 December 31
    For a pilot project testing employer-based individual development accounts delivered through local United Ways
    Grant 10401380, 2005 January 01-2006 June 30
    For training and technical assistance to local United Ways with respect to Earned Income Tax Credit outreach, for preparation services and encouraging low-income individuals to build financial assets
    - United Way of America (1020-1378), 2004-2006 (Box 8, Folder 62)
      United Way of America (10201378), 2002 July 01-2003 December 31
    - No-Cost Extension Through December 2004 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Assets for Family Success: An Employer-Based IDA Initiative, Annual Report to the Ford Foundation, Grant Number 1020-1278 and Meeting Notes, 2003 July 25 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - United Way of America - 2002 Grant (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Recommendation for Grant Action, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - United Way of America (1020-1378), 2002-2004 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - United Way of America (10401380) - Trainings for Local United Ways, 2002-2004 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - University of Michigan, 1988-2014; 10
    Grant 09801619, 1998 October 01-2011 December 31
    Continued support to recruit and train a new generation of policy researchers (910-0263)
    Grant 910-0263 was a poverty research initiative to recruit and train a new generation of poverty researchers with broad interdisciplinary perspectives, 1991 January 01-2000 August 31
    - Regents of the University of Michigan - Post Doc (0980-1619), 2005 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Regents of the University of Michigan (0980-1619) - Program Action Sheets, 1998-2003 (Box 9, Folder 70)
    - Regents of the University of Michigan (0980-1619) - Grant Status Report, 1998-2004 (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - Grants, 1988-1996 (Box 9, Folder 73)
      Regents of the University of Michigan (09100263), 1991 January 01-2000 August 31
      Poverty research initiative to recruit and train a new generation of poverty researchers with broad interdisciplinary perspectives
    - Exploring The Ways That Assets Can Change Youth's Lives: The Potential of Child Savings Accounts, Trina Shanks - Working Files, 2009-2014 (Box 89, Folder 786-787)
      Regents of the University of Michigan (10950716), 2009 September 20-2010 September 19
      For the School of Social Work to study the impact of the Saving for Education, Entrepreneurship and Downpayment (SEED) initiative on participants and their parents
    - Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy's Research and Training Program on Poverty and Public Policy Post-Doctoral Fellowship Program - Grant Number 09801619 - Working File, 2006-2014 (Box 89, Folder 788)
      Regents of the University of Michigan (09801619), 1998 October 01-2011 December 31
  - National Academy of Social Insurance (NASI), 1998-2014; 11
    Grant 10750822, 2007 May 01-2008 February 29
    To convene experts on Social Security reform and to produce a report to inform the general public, media, and policymakers
    Grant 10600860, 2006 June 01-2007 May 31
    General support for research and education on social insurance programs and diversification of its staff and board
    Grant 10500344, 2005 January 01-2006 June 30
    For public education on the importance of the Social Security Program as a financial asset and protection against the economic risks of retirement, disability and death
    Grant 10451250, 2004 September 01-2006 February 28
    To examine the problems of job loss, unemployment, and poverty and economic insecurity for older workers
    Grant 10201205, 2002 May 01-2004 April 30
    For research on the role individual savings accounts might play within Social Security